<heparin>
PTT control is 38 seconds, theraputic should be 1.5 - 2.5 x control
Petechia on chest is an adverse effect
</heparin>

<phlebitis>
Discontinue infusion and apply a warm soak, document
No need to contact the prescriber
</phlebitis>

<transfusion>
Blood should be transfused within 2-4 hours
Needle guage should be 18-20G to insure that cells aren't damaged
Monitor clients for first 15 min then periodically after 
</transfusion>

<urine>
Normal out put is 800 to 2000 mL/day ()
</urine>

<benzodiazepines>
Don't ambulate clients after administering a benzo, even to the bathroom
Don't administer an opiod after, due to risk of respiratory depression
</benzodiazepines>


<preoperative>
teaching about the procedure and experience, taching about pain and pain relief, controling client's anxiety, basic needs like elimination are met, maintain NPO status
Alert the anesthesiologist of any PO meds given prior 
</preoperative>

<multiple-sclerosis>
treatment is with beta interferon
</multiple-sclerosis>

<parkinson>
Early symptoms: fatigue, loss of smell
</parkinson>

<dialysis>
Administering an antihypertensive prior to could lead to hypotension, the nurse should wait until after dialysis to administer it.
Antimicrobials and antibiotics are removed with the dialysate solution, should be withheld until after. 
</dialysis>

<influenza>
FDA approved antivirals: peramivir, zanamivir, oseltamivir, baloxavir
Antivirals decrease the efficacy of the vaccine
</influenza>

<glasgow-coma-scale>
Assesses three areas of conciousness - verbal response, motor response, eye opening
Maximum score is 15, minimal score is 3
Eyes open (1-4): none, to pain, to speech, spontaneously
Verbal (1-5): none, incomprehensible, inappropriate, confused, oriented
Motor (1-6): none, abnormal extension, abnormal flexion, withdrawl, localizes pain, obeys commands
</glasgow-coma-scale>

<ascites>
Abdominal skin is taut and glistening
</ascites>

<bladder-distension>
Dull percussion over symphisis pubis
</bladder-distension>

<sickle-cell-crisis>
Fluids are used to reduce blood viscosity
Activity is limited to reduce oxygen needs
Diet is used to promote metabolic demand, rich in calories and high in protein
Oxygen is atministed to prevent further cell sickling
Pain management should be done with a combination of opiod and nonopiod drugs, not just nonopioid, as pain could be severe
</sickle-cell-crisis>

<low-molecular-weight-heparin>
aPTT is not used to monitor them, no frequent blood tests are required
Given to prevent lower limb blood clots
Lower risk of bleeding than heparin, but the risk is still present
</low-molecular-weight-heparin>

<LPN-duties>
All clients must be stable and require ruoutine, unchaning procedures, they cannot care for clients who require assessments 
Colostomy care
Administering oral meds
</LPN-duties>

<potassium>
Low - flattened T waves, prominent U waves, ST-segment depression, prolonged PR interval, 
</potassium>

<para-thyroid-hormone>
Primary target is the kidney and bone
Causes blood levels of calcium to rise 
Causes calcium conservation in the kidney
</para-thyroid-hormone>

<calcium>
Bound with fatty acids
</calcium>

<nsaid>
Increase blood pressure, counterindicated in individuals with hypertension
Affect platelet clotting, increase the risk of bleeding especially with 
</nsaid>

<cholelithiasis>
Risk factors include Native American and Hispanic origins, obesity, multiparousness, age over 40, fasting
</cholelithiasis>

<alcohol-withdrawal>
Signs and symptoms: elevated temperature, nocturnal leg cramps, generalized muscle pain and malaise, tremors
</alcohol-withdrawal>

<ibuprofen>
Maximum daliy dosage: 3,200 mg/day
</ibuprofen>

<statin>
Must be given at night when cholesterol production is highest
</statin>

<hemolytic-transfusion-reaction>
Symptoms: chills, low back/chest pain, hypotension, tachycardia
Treatment: stop the transfusion, obtain a urine specime, maintain blood volume and renal perfusion with an IV colloid solution (like albumin, gelatin, dextran, starch).
</hemolytic-transfusion-reaction>

<febrile-transfusion-reaction>
Temperature increase > 1 degree Celsius
Headache
Nausea/vomiting
</febrile-transfusion-reaction>

<who-do-you-see-first-rules>
Is the client stable or unstable? Eliminate stable clients.
Is the client experiencing expected or unexpeced findings? Eliminate expecting findgins. 
Are the reminaing answers referring to airway, breathing or circulation (ABCs)? Eliminate each non-priority answer option using the ABCs.
Are the reminaing asnwer options real (actual) or potential problems? Eliminate the potential problem answer options.
</who-do-you-see-first-rules>

<systemic-lupus-erythematosus>
Malar rash - rash extending across the nasal bridge and upper cheeks.
</systemic-lupus-erythematosus>

<chronic-kidney-disease>
Foods to avoid: citrus fruit, they are high in potassium as damaged kidneys cannot remove it. 
Dried fruits, avocado, tomato, potatoes and bananas. 
Calcium is lost through the damaged kidneys.
Dairy products are high in phosphorus which binds even more calcium and should be avoided.
Dietary protein incrases uric acid (urea) production which cannot be cleared by the damaged kidneys. Dietary protein should be kept at low or normal levels (but not incrased).
</chronic-kidney-disease>

<right-sided-heart-failure>
Congestion of the gastric veins, resulting in anorexia and eventual development of ascites
</right-sided-heart-failure>

<lithium-toxicity>
Early signs: nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, tremors and twitching. 
Late signs: fever, ataxia, confusion, and seizures.
</lithium-toxicity>

<fluid-intake>
Normal fluid intake should be between 1,500 - 2,000 ml/day
</fluid-intake>

<skin-grafting>
Priority should be given to grafit immobilization, since the graft must adhere to the site for vascularization to take place. It takes between 7-10 days to adhere. 
</skin-grafting>

<low-hemoglobin>
First apply oxygen to make sure the available hemoglobin is well oxygenated, place on cariac monitor, start the intravenous catheter, draw the blood work.
</low-hemoglobin>

<hyperkalemia>
Elevated T-waves
</hyperkalemia>

<cushing-disease>
Overproduction of corticosteroids, mainly cortisol or hypercortisolism. 
<cortisol> Associated with an incrase in glucose levels, increased sodium levels, decreased potassium and calcium levels. </cortisol>
</cushing-disease>



